Danny Smith

An experienced, **adaptable** and **cross-functional** developer & trainer with a passion for DevOps, agile process improvement and **helping people enjoy work**. Loves solving difficult problems, both technical and business. Has a wide range of experience, including front-end, back-end, agile coaching and SDET/QA.

Work History

Curriculum Manager & Lead Technical Instructor Sparta Global Mar 2014 - Apr 2017

 Led technical side of the academy, growing from 3-employee startup to 80+ employees taking over £1.5M GP annually.

Year 3

- Delivered 3-month multi-stream (JS Engineer/DevOps/SDET/Test) on-site academy for large media client (worth £300,000). Worked with client to define bespoke curriculum, delivered core modules and integrated graduates into tribes on completion.
- Led dev team for **microservice**-based curriculum management system built on **Sinatra**, **Node**/Express (and a little VueJS), deployed to Heroku/AWS via CI pipeline.
- Oversaw analysis and development of new 3-month Web Dev (JS/Node/CSS) and 4-month DevOps (Ruby/Microservices/Docker/Jenkins/AWS) courses.

Year 2

- Overhauled academy business processes to support scaling training delivery, clarified company vision and introduced tools to improve communication, information management and governance.
- Instructed, mentored and coached new trainers and trainees.
- Managed the quality of courseware and training delivery.

Year 1

- End-to-end design, development and pilot delivery of intensive 3-month course for agile test analysts and ruby automation engineers. Grads have been placed with clients ranging from small startups to household names.
- Focus on developing a culture of self-improvement, agile process and eloquent ruby, the modules include business skills, ISTQB certification, Web Tech (JSON, REST, Git, UNIX), Web Design (HTML, CSS, accessible RWD), Testing (Stress, JMeter, usability testing, mobile testing), Databases (Redis, Postgres, MySQL, Mongo), Core Ruby (OOP, TDD, ActiveRecord, Metaprogramming, Design Patterns), Automation (Selenium, Water, RSpec) and SBE (Cucumber/Gherkin, BDD, Framework Design)
- Design and delivery of 5-day **Agile course** (for engineering/BA/PMO streams) covering principles, Scrum, Kanban, user stories, backlog management, XP, TDD, CI, agile at scale, governance and intro to DevOps.
- Developing and maintaining in-house systems using Sinatra/RoR/Node/Express.

Test Automation Engineer

The Collinson Group Aug 2013 - Mar 2014

- Worked with agile Scrum team to improve process by introducing automated testing strategy leading towards BDD/Specification by Example.
- Developed ruby automated test framework on Cucumber, Watir/Selenium and RSpec providing fast feedback via CI and JIRA integration; helping BAs, Devs and Testers collaborate on specifications. Designed to offer long-term value, ease of use and maintainability, complex interactions are hidden behind simple Ruby interfaces.
- Developed ruby styleguide and automation engineering guidelines for company-wide use.
- Introduced **Three Amigos** workshops to in sprint planning to improve quality of user stories/acceptance criteria. Regularly led retrospectives.
- Worked with offshore teams to train and coach in basic ruby/UI automation.

Web Developer Manyhats Design *Jun 2012 - Feb 2014*

- Delivered mobile-first responsive websites using HTML5, Sass/CSS3 supported by modular styleguides and design systems such SMACSS.
- Developed back-end systems based on Sinatra and the Shopify e-commerce platform.
- Improved our design process and methodology, encouraging the use of Style Tiles and HTML prototyping.
- Focus on customer collaboration and high-quality maintainable code.

Freelance Web Developer 2006 - Jun 2012

 Collaboration with businesses to build their presence, primarily by delivering websites built in Ruby, Sinatra or Rails, Sass/CSS3, semantic HTML5 and jQuery. An early proponent of mobile-first responsive design and CSS pattern libraries.

Adjutant & Instructor

Central Training Team HQ Air Cadet Organisation April 2011 - Present (voluntary) Until 2015 I acted as Adjutant on a specialist training team tasked with qualifying Skill-at-Arms Instructors and Exercise Managers from among the 15,000 volunteer staff in the Air and Sea Cadet organisations. I still instruct on the team.

- Leading the team's instructors and managing their day-to-day work during courses.
- Maintaining the team's strategic direction and information management processes, improving business processes and rationalising policies and training materials.
- Coaching and mentoring new instructors/staff officers and encouraging a positive and enthusiastic culture.
- Internal and external quality assurance and, occasionally, the management of ACO shooting policies.
- Overseeing the development of formal performance standards and the subsequent design of a DSAT-compliant CPD programme.
- Providing expert advice on firearms training to the wider organisation.

Education, Courses and Qualifications

Licentiateship Youth Leadership & Training

City & Guilds Institute

Preparing to Teach in the Lifelong Learning Sector (QCF Level 4)

Pearson / Edexcel

Computer Science BSc

University of Sussex

Other Courses & Qualifications

- Certified Professional Scrum Master (PSM I)
- UK Government Security Clearance (SC)
- HSE First Aid at Work
- ILM Level 3 Award in First Line Management
- Full Driving License

Selected Millitary Qualifications

- Skill at Arms Instructor (Trainer)
- Exercise & Range Manager (SA(M)07, SA(SR)07, SA(LR)07)
- Qualified Drill Instructor

Other Interests

Aside from my voluntary work with the Air Cadet Organisation, I play harmonica, slide guitar & sing blues – I've had the pleasure of supporting Martin Simpson, Paul Jones & Long John Baldry, among others. I'm also a bit of a productivity geek (GTD in particular) and dabble with cryptocurrencies now and again. I write about technology on Medium.